wikileaks founder julian assange has been
arbitrarily detained by sweden and the united
kingdom since his arrest in london on 7 december
2010 as a result of the legal action taken against
him by both governments the expert panel called
on the swedish and british authorities to end
mr assange deprivation of liberty i
think the recommendation is quite clear
respect is physical integrity and freedom of
movement and afford him the right to compensation
so
okay hello everybody i'm randy credico this is
randy critical live on the fly here on 99.5 fm
in new york city uh with a very big show today
last week we had a special 90-minute program
on the first day of the assange
hearing well it's been a week now
and there was another day a lot has
happened and so thank you linda perry barr
for giving us the extra space today
this is normally a 30 minute show
but we've got 90 minutes and we have an incredible
lineup we have daniel ellsberg coming up we have
julian assange's partner mother of his two
children uh stella morris coming up and we
got bob boyle who was a witness and john kiriakou
but we're going to get underway right now with uh
one of my favorites uh ben weisner if you don't
know who he is he's the of course you know who
he is he's he's uh ed snowden's attorney he's also
the director at the acl aclu i can never do this
right with him acl speeds privacy and technology
project and he's blocked by the real donald
trump who's not online anymore or on twitter uh
hey ben uh welcome back it's been a long time
hey randy good to be here all right good uh
i i gotta tell you we've talked about this
the last time was like eight months ago and
then uh earlier that year in 2020 we we spoke
uh and you know we cover some of the same ground
uh on this assange case uh but you know the aclu
along with 25 other groups just sent a letter
uh to merrick garland uh asking for them to
dismiss the case uh before you get into that
what is your overview of what you saw last week
in london well look i think a lot is riding on
what happens in london um and you know i say
that because um none of us really wants to see
what will happen um if this case ends up back in
the u.s courtroom um you know we talk often about
how there has never been a prosecution under the
espionage act of someone for publishing truthful
information that this indictment is the first time
that the department of justice has gone down that
road but you know i recently did an event for the
50th anniversary of the pentagon papers case and
i know you're going to have daniel ellsberg on
later and he may want to add to this and we think
of the supreme court's decision in the pentagon
papers case as establishing this extremely broad
first amendment protection for journalists and in
one sense that's true it prevents the government
in almost all circumstances from blocking
publication in advance but it says nothing
to prevent the government from prosecuting
publishers and in fact the justices on
the court pretty explicitly left open
the possibility without deciding it that the
government might be able to do what it's now
doing to julian assange so we should not
see it as a done deal that if he ends up
in the u.s courtroom the first amendment will
knock out the government's case just because
this prosecution is unprecedented um doesn't mean
that it isn't extremely dangerous and we can talk
about you know more why i think this was a really
deviously chosen one to set this kind of precedent
um uh but but again many of us will be making
strong first amendment arguments if that ever
ends up here but by far the superior resolution
here would be for the uk courts to correctly rule
that this is a political offense um the espionage
act is by definition a political statute and
therefore not an extraditable offense that that um
that that in itself would set a terrible precedent
if publishers could be sent to face prosecution
for violating other countries secrecy laws so
um so we really want to see a strong ruling from
the uk courts as your listeners will remember
the courts have so far blocked his
extradition on the ground that he would
face brutal treatment in u.s prisons and
that his life would be in danger that's
of course true um but i think that it would
be a much stronger ruling if those courts said
that neither julian assange nor any other
publisher can be extradited to the united
states to face trial under the espionage act well
what makes what is going on at the department of
justice merrick garland seems like a fair-minded
individual i know somebody that i worked with who
i think was connected to the aclu who's third
in line there vanita gupta and i'm wondering
why they would continue a trump prosecution when
we thought this was going to be a new page when
biden came in look let's think about why they
might not be doing anything right now real talk
right um assange is not popular in either party
um and right now they don't feel the urgency that
they should be feeling because they know that
this case is going to be in the courts in the
united kingdom for months or years longer and my
strong belief is that there are many people in the
in the department of justice who are quietly
hoping that the british courts will take this
off the table and not force them into what
will be an extremely complicated situation
if uh the british courts green light the
extradition because then they really will
have to decide whether they want to be the
first department of justice in the history of
this country to prosecute someone for publishing
truthful information provided by somebody else
they don't have to make that decision yet
because they you know they can sit back
they can focus on their other priorities
they certainly have enough on their plate
uh and they can watch this play out in the uk
courts and if and only if the british court system
says that there's no obstacle to extradition will
this become a political problem for them that's
my belief but look and we've talked about this
before there has never been a unified u.s position
on the assange case we know there was a criminal
grand jury from the very beginning from right
after the manning leaks we know the obama
administration considered bringing a case and
ultimately decided not to because they thought
they couldn't get around what they call the new
york times problem they couldn't find a way to
construct a case against julian assange that
would not put other national security journalism
at risk even in the trump administration i'm
sure there was a difference of opinion about
whether to you know to bring these charges
some from some people in the department of
justice and others in the cia we'll talk more
about that in a minute um and uh and and some in
the fbi and and you know ultimately what you lost
was the people in the obama administration
um who put the stop sign up and the hawks
um won the day that's going to be the case again
i'm in the biden administration you're going to
have people in the fbi and the department of
justice who want to see this case go forward
and you're going to have people like
the ones you refer to a moment ago
who understand what kind of precedent it will
set so i am very very very much hoping both
because i'm worried about what will happen in
the u.s and also because i think this is an
important global precedent that the uk courts will
issue a very strong ruling against extradition
um let's go back to the yahoo news explosive
story that they put out when we were talking
he was saying in a minute talking about the cia
what kind of impact did that have on washington
if any well we'll see look i i was a little bit
surprised that the really important investigative
reporting that yahoo did uh michael isikoff and
his team was not picked up by other news outlets
because i think it was a massively important
story um and i was expecting to see the new
york times the washington post and others try to
recreate that reporting and come up with their
own visions maybe they still will um but look
you're going to hear this when you speak to daniel
ellsberg in a little while remember that there
wasn't one pentagon papers case there were two
yes go ahead tell us there was a case where
the nixon administration tried unsuccessfully
to prevent the new york times and washington
post and others from publishing the papers
and then there was the criminal case against
dan and that case was never concluded because
the judge in that case dismissed the charges
with prejudice meaning they couldn't be refiled
on the basis of outrageous government conduct and
what was that outrageous government conduct it was
all kinds of things but principally it was about
surveillance of daniel ellsberg's attorneys and
their attorney client relationship breaking into
his psychiatrist's office um all of these kinds of
um dirty tricks um that were in this yahoo news
article so so if these kinds of facts um were
put before a judge in the u.s i hope what he would
do right away is hold an evidentiary hearing and
haul the government into court and make them
give a full accounting of whether they conducted
surveillance on assange's attorneys we know they
have in the embassy whether they have records of
that relationship being compromised what they
can say about it if they can't demonstrate that
assange's right to counsel wasn't compromised by
their bad acts then this prosecution should not
go forward but look before we even talk about
what effect it will have in the u.s courts i
really hope that this provides even a stronger
basis for the course in the united kingdom to say
um this is definitely not an extradition
that should happen this case is just it
stinks to high heaven well you know they're
spending a lot of money they're going against
i mean someone's just got x amount of money you're
dealing with a mammoth uh organization which is
the justice department and the crown prosecutor
services they got endless supply of money uh where
how does assange fight this legally i know there's
a lot of volunteer attorneys but there's a lot of
paperwork and there's a lot of investigating to
go on let's say he's he's he's he's got some of
the finest lawyers in the united kingdom who are
on his side um the one thing that i'm not worried
about is his having the best defense that's
available to him uh because there's an all-star
team of lawyers who are in his corner both in the
uk and in countries around the world who are you
know standing by ready to do their part when
they're called upon that that doesn't bother
me i mean we're always used to having you know the
aclu is huge in the united states but we're just a
few hundred lawyers the justice department is 11
000. right that's what i'm talking about there's
so many layers the quality of the arguments and
right now um that that is at the bottom of my list
of concerns here's what's higher on my list of
concerns and again we've talked about this before
um the united states is in court in
the united kingdom making the argument
that an australian publisher needs to be sent
to virginia to be prosecuted for the felony of
breaking the united states secrecy
laws think about that for a minute
that the united states is making
the claim that its own secrecy laws
bind foreign publishers criminally um and that
they can be forced in chains to fly to the united
states and go to prison for violating u.s secrecy
laws um so much of what we're talking about when
we talk about these kinds of prosecutions is
about precedents and traditions not necessarily
black letter law what precedent is it going to
set if one of the leading democratic nations
um extradites a foreign journalist and publisher
to be prosecuted for violating secrecy laws
and what ground will we have to object if
china if iran if azerbaijan if any country
in the world says we now want to extradite a
guardian journalist we now want to extradite
a new york times journalist because they published
our country's secrets in violation of our laws
now i i'm not suggesting that that extradition
would happen i'm just suggesting that the united
states would have no principle basis for denying
it right what what are do we have daniel on the
other line is he there do we have we we actually
have daniel but we have stella morris in one
minute i'm gonna be uh kind of extemporizing this
at this point it's an embarrassment of riches for
you randy well that's a good all right okay i
want to just see if he's there if daniel's there
can you hear us dan i'm here i can hear you can
you hear me yes yes we got stella morris coming
on i just want her to know we're going to spend
a few more minutes and get you on in like five or
six minutes uh i know i know ben was just
talking you missed the first 15 minutes why
don't you gentlemen say hello to each other it's
been a long time hi ben hi good to hear from you
i wish i'd heard from any any news that
i miss okay no we're not on the air are
we yes we are we are on the air we just want to
make sure you were on the air because i know uh
we uh we we have you there is stella on the air do
we have her i want to make sure all right so we're
waiting for stella morris to get on the air i'm
going to have to uh continue with you guys uh that
which is a good thing daniel um let me ask you uh
right now ben just laid it all out the dangerous
precedent this would set and and uh why don't
you kind of take it from there what you think
uh would happen if assange is brought over here
and successfully prosecuted and sent to prison
yes first of all i suspect ben would know more
than this but i suspect that contrary to their
assurances if they don't send him to australia
uh he'll be in isolation uh just the way chelsea
manning was for ten and a half months until a
popular pressure got her off mordecai vanunu
my friend in israel was kept in isolation for 10
and a half years out of his 17 years that he got
for revealing israeli nuclear program and i
think they would take the attitude that julian
has information still to give that he hasn't put
out they don't want him in the general population
that's just my guess but the precedent in terms
would be the very first time that a journalist
had been prosecuted for telling the truth
to the american people they've avoided that
they've considered it often as a matter of fact
in my own trial in which back in 1971 to 73 when
i was the first person to be prosecuted under the
espionage act same charges as julian is facing now
for giving top secret information to the american
people none of which was ever demonstrated or even
plausibly claimed to have harmed national security
meaning it should not have been classified but in
any case at that very time nixon was trying to
had a grand jury looking into prosecuting neil
sheehan and hedrick smith of the new york times
and probably others and that uh grand jury ended
was was terminated we don't know exactly why
but probably for the same reasons that my
trial was ended finally the discovery of illegal
wiretapping of us and perhaps other intrusions
in my case the trial has ended in large part
because of discovery of government crimes against
me that have been considered or perpetrated
against julian specifically uh illegal wiretapping
in julian's case surveillance of him even his
lawyers conferences and his doctors conferences in
the ecuadorean embassy going just the information
going to cia and then consideration discussion of
assassinating him or kidnapping or poisoning him
either kidnapping or killing him by poisoning
in my case a dozen cia assets were brought up
from miami bay of pigs veterans to incapacitate
me ellsberg totally which meant either killing me
or shutting me up i think was probably the latter
the special prosecutor felt their intention was
to kill me and when that came out my charges were
dropped and more importantly those figured in
the impeachment of richard nixon and made the
war endable when he resigned facing impeachment
obviously julian's trial should be terminated the
charges should be terminated just on those
grounds alone just as mine was and however
if as you say they do bring him back that will set
a precedent it will not be the last we know that
a previous president would have
certainly continued with other
with other uh prosecutions but that
appears to be true of biden as well
a few people have really commented on just
how outrageous it is that president joe biden
a democrat or liberal is carrying
on this blatant up contradiction
violation of the first amendment of freedom
of the priest press freedom of speech which
is the basis of our democracy and uh for trump
to do that is somehow not surprising it was
predicted by the aclu even before he got in that
he would build on the president of president obama
bringing many cases like mine against sources
to the press but obama refrained from doing that
in the case of julian because it was so obviously
a blatant violation of the first amendment much so
even more so than in my case and by the way
there's strong legal opinion that to use it
against me and the others that obama did was
already unconstitutional and the supreme court
has never ruled on that it has not come up to this
it's come up but they have rejected uh hearing it
so it's never been ruled as to whether
that use of the espionage act against
whistleblowers is constitutional and the earlier
supreme court would almost surely have ruled
that it was constant unconstitutional
obviously with the present supreme court
you can't count on their taking
the bill of rights very seriously
so it could be that we would lose the first
amendment essentially and live like most countries
in the world on government handouts when it comes
to information about what the government is doing
in our name especially in the area of so-called
national security so it's extremely serious uh
problem here which the press i have to say has
been very derelict generally in not recognizing
that this is aimed directly at them that julian
is not distinct from other members of the press
as some have wanted to imply his precedent would
clearly be used to prosecute other journalists
we're talking with daniel ellsberg and ben
weissner of the aclu uh ben uh listen i'm
uh working on getting stella on i want you to uh
either riff on that or ask mr ellsberg a question
if you would well i just just to riff on that
for a second i mean dan is absolutely right that
the central questions of this case have never
been resolved by the us supreme court which is
um the reason why i think both of us fear this
particular case being the first one that would
go up um because of the cross partisan hostility
here but but dan as i said earlier on the show
it's not just that the supreme court has
never ruled on whether the espionage act
can be used against the source in the original
pentagon papers litigation it left open whether
it could be used against the publisher that was
not resolved in new york times versus united
states either so we shouldn't be confident as dan
suggested that the first amendment will solve our
problems if this case washes up on our shores by
far the better chance here and the stronger hope
um is that the courts in the united kingdom um
will refuse to extradite both on the humanitarian
grounds and on the very strong legal ground that
this is a political offense that should not be
extraditable damn ben can i ask you something this
is ironic i'm i'm glad to hear you say that they
have a good basis for refusing exhibition on those
grounds isn't it the case that in england with the
official secrets act uh either i or but or even
julian would be clearly held to be in violation
they they have an official secrets act we don't
we have a first amendment they don't that was a
product of the american war of independence uh is
that wrong no am i wrong it's right it's right i
mean the problem is that as we have both commented
over the years the espionage act has been creeping
closer to being an official secrets act at least
as to people who work for the government um
but this is the case if you read carefully
the opinions in new york times versus united
states which was the pentagon papers and junction
case the court leaves open expressly leaves open
the possibility that the new york times or others
could be held criminally liable after the fact
even though they can't be enjoined before the
fact and we haven't in these last 50 years seen
a single instance of that because of the culture
of the first amendment in the united states and
the recognition by the department of justice
that the there is massive over classification
the public has a right and need to know lots of
uh important secrets but this is the case that
could break things open um you have democrats
that don't like julian because they blame him
for trump being elected you have republicans
who are very enthusiastic about setting a
precedent that prosecutors can be reported so
of all cases to go to the supreme court to test
these vital principles this would be the worst
one yes you know am i that's you've really
turned my head around in a bad way um ben
because i've always thought of those oberder
dicta if they're i believe they're called in the
supreme court where people made the comment the
justices made the comment five four in particular
and five by implication that there could be a
prosecution i've always read that as uh allowing
a prosecution of me a source are you saying that
they left open the prosecution of the new york
times yes very much i just did an event with bert
newborn who you know um uh formerly of the aclu
who represented the aclu in that case and and
and he said the very same thing that that what
we've had in this country is not um a legal
precedent that's prevented these prosecutions
but a very very strong constitutional tradition
that has prevented these prosecutions look i think
and we would raise very strong first amendment
argument if this prosecution ever happens um and
i'm not suggesting that we would necessarily lose
those i'm just saying that the fact that there
has never been a prosecution of a publisher under
the espionage act is not because there is any
holding of the supreme court that would prevent it
right well i i knew there was no holding
that would prevent it what you're telling me
is that they made comments that not only opened
the way to the prosecution which occurred i was
prosecuted but uh that that they would have they
were actually allowing let's say the grand jury
proceedings they were going against nick uh rick
smith and neil sheen at that time and i i really
had never thought of that my own thought about
those of course i read those opinions at the time
and my own thought i was not happy of course that
they were almost calling for my prosecution on
this uh unnecessarily they didn't have to say
anything about that but um i put it down to the
ignorance of these supreme court justices like
all other lawyers to the law and the application
of this of any act including theft or espionage
act to leaking because there never had been a case
i've talked to large audiences of judges in the
past believe it or not and lawyers and journalists
on separate occasions and found that almost none
of them really knew anything of the background
of the first amendment law in this case but
especially the espionage act and that was natural
they hadn't studied it in law school at all there
were no cases and that's the situation the supreme
court found itself in several of them complaining
about it that in a matter of days or a couple
of weeks they were addressing these things for
the first time and so i thought okay they made
those comments but maybe they wouldn't stand up
later you're not you're not encouraging me we'll
see look uh you'll you'll remember and randy
please cut in when stella is ready um and and
interrupt us because dan and i can speak to each
other all day yeah yeah i understand that it's
okay she's uh there's some kind of transmission
problem they're waiting but we're gonna go to the
uh you guys stick with us we're gonna go
to the news we have to take a news break
right now a short news break can you guys both
stick around sure sure okay we'll be right back
okay i'm randy credico this is randy critical
live on the fly 99.5 fm wbai free speech radio in
new york city here in brooklyn um our friends
over there in london i i think you may want
to unmute uh i think you might be on mute so
uh please uh unmute because we'd love to be
uh listening to you as well we have uh this
is a special edition of uh assange's countdown
to freedom here at wbai we are talking
right now with ben weisner of the aclu
and the great whistleblower mr daniel ellsberg
thank you gentlemen for holding on and just
can you kind of continue uh where you left off
before i know weisner you got a bookmark on it
dan what were we talking about man i have
a question for you did you agree with me
what i just said that it's particularly
outrageous that a democratic president
is pursuing this particular case yes um i i
do as i said before you joined i think they're
not feeling any sense of urgency because they
know that it's going to be tied up in the uk
courts for months or years probably some of them
quietly hope that it will be resolved there so
that they won't have to make a decision whatever
decision they make is going to be unpopular with
some people in their own party and so they
would prefer i think for this to be handled
in the courts in the united kingdom and then
of course there are others as there always have
been including democrats who have wanted to bring
this case um the obama administration ultimately
decided not to do it but that's not because there
weren't people who were pushing for it internally
there were many people who were pushing for it
they had wait let's let's name names there for
a minute i think we can assume hillary clinton is
one of those and conceivably that influenced biden
he's vice president she was secretary of state
but let's see do you mind naming names who
besides hillary clinton in the democratic
party wants to see the first amendment uh
stopped and julian convicted who who
would that look i'm not i'm not i'm
not just talking about elected officials
in the democratic party i'm talking about
people who work in the fbi people who work at the
u.s attorney's office in the national security
division of the department of justice right okay
always been a debate in government this has never
been a uniform decision there were always
people who were pushing for this prosecution
and at the end of the day it was people on
the political side and eric holder who said
we can't get around the new york times problem we
can't prosecute julian assange without exposing
other national security journalists to criminal
liability for doing their work there's no way
that we won't be loading that weapon to be used
against other journalists there's still plenty
of people who work for those agencies but i also
think that you know if you look at the democrats
who sit on the intelligence committees in the
house and senate not all of them but certainly
plenty of them um they would be delighted to
see this case go forward okay you've answered
yeah i understand right the the the incredibly
dishonest investigations and reports they put
out about snowden um you know tell you that i mean
these people are very much um doing the opposite
of oversight over the intelligence agencies uh
they get the most donations from the security
contractors and i i i mean the real question
is who will be the first democrats in congress
to stand up and denounce this prosecution
because so far we haven't really seen any
god that's terrible well yeah you know
you say democrats oddly enough i think
ron paul and randy paul both both criticized that
in fact they're among the only two members of
congress who ever said anything favorable about
me in public i've met plenty of them at their
fundraisers or shaking hands or even taking a
photo which i notice if they're willing to do that
but in terms of saying it in an interview or in
congress no uh rand paul and ron paul are the
only ones that come to my mind well let me ask you
guys here about the media you know we we are on it
uh pacifica in san francisco dennis bernstein
has done plenty uh we've been doing this here
for five years i know there are people who give us
some heat over it but uh you take a look let me i
don't want to name names myself but airy melbourne
seemed to be very interested in me when i was
supposedly the back channel which i wasn't there
was no back channel but msnbc has totally dropped
the ball isn't this like leaving in my opinion a
guy in the trenches and going awol because so so
two things randy i mean first of all i will say
this that the major news organizations when the
second indictment of julian assange was released
that included um felony charges for publication
not this really concocted really contrived kind of
hacking charge which is factually nonsense but but
uh but that charged him under the espionage
for publication most of the major media
outlets condemned that and said that it would be a
threat but they haven't done two other things that
would be really vitally important and helpful
number one they're not reporting on it enough
um they actually need to be raising a stink um
it's it's they got scooped by yahoo on a big
story but they haven't followed up and they're
not covering um the proceedings in the uk
closely enough this should be a huge story in the
united states and it hasn't been and number two
uh the the corporate side the owners the people
who own dow jones and the wall street journal
and nbc um and the new york times should be going
to the white house and saying that this case is an
existential threat to national security
investigative journalism um and i'm not saying
the reporters i'm saying the owners the people who
who hobnob with the the president in his circle
they're the ones who should be putting
this at the top of their agenda
and not things like you know don't be rude to
us at press conferences um or don't kick us out
of the white house right this this case um if
it proceeds and you know they they should not
sit back and say oh we're different we wouldn't do
the things that he did because as dan said before
if this case proceeds to conviction not only are
we going to see more prosecutions of publishers
and journalists but there's going to be a massive
chilling effect because the lawyers for those
institutions are going to know that prosecution
is possible and they are going to advise
the editorial side to be much much more cautious
in their reporting and that's going to be the
biggest impact well and ben that reminds me
i'm gonna i rarely addressed as you just did
very well the media role in this but let me
uh make two points very one very personal
during my trial which lasted two years and
had it just we had to raise a lot of money
in the course of that there were two grand
juries involved there were people who had to be
housed and fed during the
trial for essentially two years
the new york times never mentioned in the times
in any story about the case and we were in that
we were on the front page during the actual
court proceedings every day never mentioned
there was a defense fund let alone suggesting no
member of the new york times picked up a phone
and the publishers you know knew everyone picked
up the phone and suggested anybody that this was
a good case to support and actually the times
lawyers refused to give my lawyers any of their
briefs that they any any research material they'd
collected for the supreme court case as one member
of the new york times said to a to another lawyer
who a young lawyer who suggested they do that
it's one thing to defend the new york times
it's another thing to defend a traitor and uh
the uh they just didn't do it so and meanwhile
there was uh a scurrilous uh slanderous story
about me in the uh in the magazine section
which was the basis for my warning julian
don't be so shocked by the way they're treated
you that's what they do with every whistleblower
essentially keep absolute arms arms length
but the more the other thing i was saying was
about journalists oh no i'm sorry i
didn't say this i rarely have said it
in this connection i think there is a symbiosis
between the media and the secrecy system
and that's not obvious i think they're uh it
works very well for them they like to say uh as
various uh editors have said well
the government tries to keep secrets
we try to get them there's kind of
a balance it's good for democracy
nonsense the government wins that enormously
more of the time than is good for democracy
why would the press go along with that let me just
make a guess i'm not a journalist i'm a source but
my impression is that when they are told as
happens every day when a an official of the
government tells a reporter a secret something
that's classified something they would not put out
in a press conference and they do this
all the time to serve their legislative
program or to serve an agency benefit or to
grant make better the reputation of a
particular official they do it all the time
when they give them that exclusive it's an
exclusive because it's not given in a press
conference and so the reporter gets that scoop
of high officials usually they can't name them
high officials but their editor editors know who
it is so they know they've got something here
uh say this and then the next week uh and know
that other reporters don't have that story because
it's classified it has not been declassified
by giving it to that particular reporter
then the next week that official gives another
secret to another reporter well that's okay with
the first one because his term will come again
if he's a good boy if he doesn't criticize if
he doesn't quote anybody who contradicts what
this official has just told him he'll get his
scoop again so i think they like the fact that
uh they're able to get news on an exclusive basis
because of the classification system information
that should never have been held secret at all
and that the the public deserve to have uh or
needed in some cases now that's my guess as i
say as a non-journalist maybe randy you are well
i'm not a journalist wait a second i don't think
anyone's ever taken me seriously i'm a radio host
and i'm a political satirist and uh sorry i didn't
mean to insult you no no but you know i'm i don't
do any investigative reporting you know what yahoo
news did that was investigative reporting
we had alan dortmund now there are a lot of
what do you call it alternative media outlets
out there that have done stories on assange but
i know this story that emerged by yahoo news
took like dorfman said it was like almost a
year ago when they got their first tip on it so
they really did their job and there's a lot of
substance to that story uh gentlemen uh i i
i want don't go anywhere we're talking with
uh the great ben wisner and the great legendary
whistleblower daniel ellsberg and joining us now
because there's been a lot of talk about what kind
of uh trial would emerge in the eastern district
of virginia and alexandria and someone who knows
about that system uh you know over i don't know if
you know him ben but i know that uh mr ellsberg
does and that is john karioko who has a radio
show coming up soon so uh he's on the other
line we're still waiting for stella i hope you
can hear us and please unmute or reconnect john
kiriakou welcome to live on the fly here on wbai
again thanks randy thanks for having me and what
an honor and a pleasure it is to be with with the
great dan ellsberg and the great ben weissner
my pleasure all right well listen uh ben you've
been doing a good job uh asking questions i'm
going to let you you're a journalist on the side
uh you're you're you're you're handing me the
mic yeah i'm going to let you hand the mic
because i thought john and i have spoken a million
times uh to bring john into this conversation
so i think um one of the things that dan and i
were just talking about john before you joined
is really where is the media here um we've seen
some comments upon the original release of the
indictment where they said look this is a threat
to investigative journalism but they haven't done
um um by my account two other things they
haven't been lobbying at a high level for
these charges to be dropped and they haven't
really been covering um julian's case as the
existential threat to national security journalism
that it is so you obviously have um have quite
a bit of experience with the media on this
and and what's your read on why um there's
just you know why even national security
journalists who should understand the stakes
um are not covering these proceedings more closely
you know i think it's that well it's a couple of
things but the first thing that pops into my
head is the fact that so few news outlets have
a budget for investigative journalism anymore that
what they do is they essentially crawl into bed
with the cia they'll take cia pronouncements and
cia press releases and gist them and and call it
journalism we know from jason leopold for example
at buzzfeed that uh that there are supposedly a
level journalists who send their their articles
to the cia for clearance uh like ken delanian does
uh before he even sends them to his own editor so
i think a lot of this is they don't have the the
wherewithal or even necessarily the desire to uh
to really do real journalism and the other thing
too is that i think that they're afraid of the cia
at the same time i happened to participate in a
in a zoom call the other day with a bunch of
attorneys and self-professed and intellectuals
and a handful of journalists and there was
a journalist there from from knight ritter
and one of the attendees asked him specifically
why haven't you and others spoken out on behalf of
julian assange we're spoken about the conditions
that julian assange is suffering through or or
even spoken about uh the issues that have gotten
julian assange into his current predicament
and the guy came right out and said because
julian assange is an activist not a journalist
and the questioner said even even if you
don't think that he's a journalist you have to
acknowledge that he's a publisher and the guy said
you know what i don't want to talk about julian
assange and to me that that said that they're
just afraid they're afraid of provoking the cia
or the justice department and they're hoping that
if they just remain silent this thing will go away
and not affect them right we're talking john can i
ask you john because you you would know this point
i made if you heard it earlier that uh the
secrecy system actually serves the media to a
considerable extent because it provides them with
a flow of exclusives to one reporter at a time
which gives them scoops which are very
highly prized and therefore the fact
that the classification system is keeping that
information from being given to other people
simultaneously is very hopeful uh helpful
do you see anything in that i think you are
exactly right on that score washington runs
on leaks if you pick up the washington post
or the new york times any day of the week
you'll see ostensibly classified information
the the george w bush administration's
classifications are bill leonard says that
that we have hundreds of millions of classified
documents that ought not be classified
but they're classified just because just
because they can be and because they can
be used almost as currency as you said correctly
dan where the cia and others can just dole the
information out to preferred journalists
give them a scoop and have the agency's
story or the agency's version of a story be the
story of record that's actually a felony what many
americans don't understand is that it's illegal
to improperly classify information in the united
states of course nobody's ever been prosecuted for
it it's one of those laws that's been on the books
forever that that nobody pays any attention to
but the cia and others can use it to their benefit
if anyone has ever been demoted uh or in any way
administratively punished or reprimanded for over
classifying a document i'd like to hear of it
i've never heard of one not only have they not
been prosecuted i don't think they've they've ever
had anything to suffer in their career from making
something talk secret that shouldn't be classified
and i'll tell you another thing too along those
same lines um i sat next to a woman in the 1990s
when i was at the cia who was dating a former cia
senior cia officer who went on to become a talking
head at cnn and in the course of pillow talk she
divulged to him classified information that
he then repeated on the air okay well we know
ever since the obama administration that's the
very definition of an espionage charge right the
obama people would have charged her with espionage
and certainly the trump people would have as well
so what happened to the woman uh she was called
down to security they asked her did you pass
this information to your boyfriend she said yes
they suspended her without pay for four weeks
and the letter went into her file saying that she
couldn't be promoted for one year well now well
you've given me example there then there's one
person that's uh more than i've heard of it before
i don't think they would have done that if it
weren't something they didn't want out if it
was something that uh served the purposes of
cia or the white house policy or whatever uh
then she would have been more than uh more
than reprimanded but uh when the the the media
have never uh or really anybody else but congress
or the press have not investigated the secrecy
system as it should be investigated because it's
not just a matter of some abuses the system itself
is an abuse a source of abuses to an enormous
extent in in my trial we called as a witness a man
named william florence of florence who had just
retired and he had just given testimony under oath
to the congress uh government information
committee on the secrecy system because he had
written most of the regulations in the pentagon
over a 30-year career and so he came and gave
the same testimony under oath that he given to the
congress which was this that five percent of the
information that was classified he said deserved
classification at the time it was classified
he said within a few years it was one-tenth
of that half a percent so everybody agrees
all the time there's over classification maybe
20 maybe 30 maybe 50 try 95 or 99 and a half uh
the the presumption that people have when
something classified is put out uh without
authorization that uh not the kind of uh that it
hurts national security to have that out that is
not should not be the presumption and in addition
to the reasons you gave john you have to add
uh the fact or i'm sorry it was randy you have to
add uh that so much of it not all of it of course
but so much that is classified is classified
indefinitely because it would reveal deception
even criminality violation of treaties as
in the pentagon papers case for example
uh enormous what snowden revealed enormous
violation of the force of fourth amendment
domestic criminality as you revealed uh
torture a uh without even meaning to you know
do anything that violated the regulations but uh
he revealed as i understand the name of somebody
who had been in vail involved in torture uh should
that really have been concealed remember that the
entire torture report six thousand pages of the
senate intel the committee on torture remains
classified we have only the executive highly
redacted executive summary of that and to this day
it's not been released that's that's why it's all
it's all domestic crime and international crime
every page of that i would imagine reveals that
and that's why it's classified and dan that's why
authorities at nsa for example or at
cia have been forced to come out and say
that the information that chelsea manning revealed
or that ed snowden revealed did not cause any harm
to the national security because it was improperly
classified in the first place there's no reason
for example that reality winner should have
gone to prison that was an analytic document
that should never have been classified in the
first place it was only classified because
somebody from nsa had written it that's not a
reason to spend someone said to send somebody
to prison for five years and four months right
but we see that every day the system is is broken
well i'm not sure it's broken it does
what it does what it's meant to do
it it keeps information from the public
not just that needn't be classified that's
the most of it needn't be classified but it
keeps from the public information the public
particularly needs to know that would hold the
officials accountable for deceptions for crimes
for false predictions let's say all of
that has to be kept classified to avoid
embarrassment so the system is working to do
what it really is meant to do not what the
regulations say about national security but the
reason that it's really there works very well
i'm going to have to leave this conversation in
danielle's burns and john kiryaku's able hands
randy i've been on 45 minutes longer than you
expected yes well i know but you did a magnificent
job filling in for me we finally got uh stella
there so we're going to say goodbye to you uh and
we're going to say goodbye thank you very much ben
you were fantastic and uh we'll see you soon and
john i know you got to get to work and uh uh you
have anything else to say do we have stella now
i think she's i just want to say to keep up the
good work i can't imagine a more important cause
than than the life and the freedom of julian
assange and uh i know that this is a process i
know it's gonna take maybe another year but in
my gut in my heart i know that we're gonna be
victorious because julian did nothing wrong okay
hey that's uh john kiriakou thank you i want to
thank ben weisner uh dan you're going to stick
around here uh and uh good luck we'll be talking
you to you soon uh mr kiriakou i'm randy credico
this is randy critical live on the fly and at last
we do have and this is my fault because i thought
there was a five hour difference between here in
london there's only a four hour difference because
they changed the time and we do have now uh human
rights attorney stella morris you're still
there dan right yes okay so stick around don't
go anywhere dan uh we are joined now by stella
morris who is the partner of julian assange and
the mother of his two children uh welcome stella
hi randy hi dan how are you hi hi all right well
you know i guess there is only a four-hour
difference there stella we've been talking uh
for the last hour on this case and i know you've
gone through a lot and i don't want to get into
all of that but people here don't know what to do
at this point in time many of us we feel hamstrung
and i know that you have some advice
what people can do and which includes
supporting the defense fund so why don't you
uh give us an overview of what we can do here
right um well julian is you know it's really a
david against goliath battle here because the way
um the the case is rigged against him in so
many ways uh the u.s the doj has had you know
uh 11 years to try to mount a case they
haven't been able to mount a case but
they've been able to issue an indictment
and and issue an extradition warrant
and the uk then represents the us in
court and the uk taxpayer pays for
the us government's uh bogus case against uh
julian and then julian has to raise his own funds
to mount to defense so it's it's a it's a david
against goliath battle in many different aspects
but the financial one is one and that's a way
that um people can very meaningfully uh contribute
uh to julian's defense into his freedom yeah uh
let me just you know dan you were talking earlier
about your defense fund how difficult it was to
raise money but people did come forward uh and
give money to the daniel ellsberg defense fund if
i'm not correct absolutely 25 000 people actually
contributed to it and that was at a time when they
had every reason to think that would put them on
a government list of some kind has had happened
in the past but it was a very wide participation
and and stella so how do people uh and i'm asking
everybody out there i know the legal battle i
know the lawyers there's a lot of lawyers
but there's a lot of paperwork they still
have a lot of obstacles ahead of them and how do
people actually make i know they can do it here
with nyc free assange they have it on their
front page to make a donation to the assange
defense team how do they do it otherwise well the
the easiest way is to just go to my twitter feed
which is a stella morris one morris with one r um
and my pinned tweet there is the the crowd justice
fundraiser that i have set up the the money there
goes to to julian's extradition uh legal team
and i post updates there um periodically
uh during the hearings it's it's daily and
uh you get an email with with my updates uh and
alerts and so on um and of course there's uh um
the defense uh website with with more details and
if people want to donate uh via cryptocurrency
there's also that option and if they don't
know how to donate uh or if um have some
specific uh requests about the way they want
to donate they can always contact me directly
over twitter dm i have open dms and there's always
a way that stella morris with 1r stella m-o-r-i-s
one at twitter that's one way you can get and
and and i'll ask both of you i mean you're going
against uh you know two huge you know the endless
supply of money we're talking about the cps crown
prosecutor services in in the uk and in here you
got the justice department how much money i mean
do they have dan uh i mean you're facing a giant
here money-wise you know in a way people can ask
uh how can it be that they can are pursuing julian
this way for as you say 11 years and one answer is
that julian as david did take on the goliath he
was actually threatening the veil of secrecy that
protects criminality and imperialism and torture
as he revealed uh chelsea manning was giving him
information on that death squads all over the
world and that was a threat to every pretty
much every country in the world especially those
that are more imperial than others so in a way
he was taking on the world establishment the
ruling class the the imperial powers and it's uh
shouldn't be a surprise that they're
throwing all this at him and that they'll
never forgive him and the on the other side stella
uh if i may say i i really thank you because as a
friend of as a friend of julian though that it
is your loving support and your support of his
children your children that is keeping him alive
so i really want to thank you for your for that
thanks donna i i think he it's
it's our love for each other that's
kind of been an amazing uh
thing in this in this in the middle of this
nightmare um but you know julian also has so much
support around the world and whenever i see
him or speak to him i make sure to tell him
about you know the the many different actions
uh people you know from from the grassroots
but also organizations that are more and more
organizations are coming on board and making
um gestures like uh the german section of of
penn international yesterday made julian an
honorary member on the day of the international
day against impunity of crimes against journalists
and it's that kind of thing it's just building
and building i just noticed today that the the uh
uk the us and australia who have this
thing called the in the media freedom
initiative they issued a statement about
um uh killing killings of journalists and
persecution of journalists and and this to me it's
it's uh it's not really a sign of hypocrisy i've
i've kind of evolved in my um understanding of
what they're doing it's just deflection they're
trying to regain control of the narrative because
it's slipping away because the the prosecution of
julian is such a clear political persecution
um and it's it's plain for everyone to see
dan dan you want to respond to that well i
i i agree that uh you know he deserves that
support and he as i'm saying he should be getting
a lot more than he is with the help of the media
we're not joining him but stella i'll tell
you as i've listened to you i'm thinking this
that uh a book that came out about whistleblowers
and they've been innumerable whistleblowers in the
civil field which also involves a lot of death
like tobacco and uh the sacklers uh oxycontin
where by the way there seems to have been very
few uh whistleblowers uh on the oxycontin case
but in most of those cases i said the lifespan
of a marriage was 18 months according to this
energy it almost in in in my time uh there weren't
that many whistleblower cases but the uh anti-war
resistors who went to prison mostly it broke
up marriages the strain was just too great and
it didn't and the people hadn't signed on for that
and uh it was bad for the marriage my case is very
unusual there or patricia and i were if anything
closer we've just had our 50th anniversary and
jeffrey sterling was very much supported by his
wife and john my understanding if john has left
but john kiriakou's marriage uh helping support
him during that well in your case you joined
him during this case and as i said before i'm
sure that it's that support that is keeping him
really sane and alive uh under under extremely
bad conditions i is one i am one of the few
whistleblowers uh from a national security
field who did not suffer personal consequences
essentially although the government had those
in mind i was faced with a possible 115 years
in prison nothing compared to julian's 175
but in terms of our lifespan probably come
to the same thing but in my case by almost a
miracle uh nixon was deprived of his ability to
ruin my life uh didn't didn't do it at all
but in many cases of course it has done
that and so i come back to the thought
that i really appreciate stella uh your
your support and i've talked to his father uh john
shipton is his half-brother gabriel and of course
they've made a tour over here for funding for him
and i'm i'm very glad you're making the pitch for
funding and i was just thinking that i
i was derelicted not raising it myself
all right well you know what we're talking with
uh with daniel ellsberg and stella morris human
rights attorney uh and you can i want to say it
again you can donate to the campaign the defense
team here and and let me just put in its
nyc free assange here they have a donate
button that goes straight to what stella has just
mentioned but you can also go to and you should
follow her because you'll get like incredible
information that's uh at stella morris with oner
one on twitter and i urge everybody
out there please please support
this defense team it's really vital at this
point in time and and stella uh let me talk about
uh other actions there are uh groups there's uh
here in new york the kurds foundation you got
the defend assange uh you've got other groups
and dc and denver you got them in san francisco
and what's your message to them because they're
looking a lot of them what do we do at this point
well we need to get the congressional
representatives uh aware that people are
outraged about this case and want it to be dropped
that involves you know making the people regular
people aware of what this case is if you know you
have a cafe or a bar or whatever set up a petition
gather signatures get you know information
um to people go to the rallies um and get you
know good information because um follow me follow
wikileaks um follow the dea campaign um the the uh
uh accounts that that um i i promote are
good sources for information and you know
don't expect um the media to be on top of this
case because they've failed failed dismally yahoo
news did an excellent investigation and um the
main many of the um well some of the channels did
do good coverage of it cbs did a very good report
um to their credit uh the new york times tried to
avoid it they mentioned it for the first time only
after it had been mentioned in the extradition uh
case on thursday um and then it was mentioned
uh so you know that they can't uh avoid the the
uh the true nature of this case um forever but in
the meantime we have to stay informed proactively
absolutely and if there's anything else i know
i know it's getting late there and and you got
you got family obligations at this point
um and so if there's anything dan you want
to ask her before we take a break and
bring in one of the witnesses robert
boyle is going to and i want you to stick
around dan do you have for uh miss morris
just this is uh maybe bad news i don't want
to raise it but but i will that is it the case
that we expect or is ben still here i would ask
if ben no ben's not here ben's gone oh but i
is it the case that the government is like is able
to appeal if this goes in favor of julian which
means that he would have to stay in prison anyway
if they if they do go in favor of julian is that
the case they can they can try to appeal to the
supreme court um and then the supreme court could
choose to hear it or not um i mean right now we're
we're faced with two prospects one is that um
that julian could um win uh and that he could lose
and if he loses this could go on for a long time
uh even if he wins there's a there's a risk
that um he could be you know snatched um and
the it's possible that he could be extradited
um to the us uh before the summer as well so
we're both prospects of julian remaining in prison
for a long time or um you know being snatched uh
are are terrifying and basically the baden biden
administration has to drop this case well that
gives us another deadline here if the if they do
rule in favor of him that would be the time for
a heavy widespread pressure as much as possible
on biden not to appeal that ruling to a higher
court you know if we'd have another crack at that
if if if we face that is that right sounds right
yeah that's right um but i mean either way this
the the yahoo story uh sets uh uh there's a
there's a before and after this uh yahoo story
about the uh plans to kill uh julian by the
cia under pompeo by the way obviously congress
should be investigating that these well-supported
allegations of criminal activity uh by the cia and
others uh against an american citizen and uh they
should be investigating that and they're derelict
if they don't but i one last question general when
have has julian been able to see his
children face to face under these conditions
he has yeah and um we we go to the prison um
uh once a week more or less and he's able to
hold the kids and and read them stories and
you know they love they love going and and
seeing him and and it's really nice when when
they're together and just through for about
an hour and then we go back to this madness well
i hope they may be too young to to know but i hope
they will learn how many people in the world
are supporting their father we got to continue
that support folks and as i said i want to say
it again here in uh the u.s if you don't aren't
on twitter you can go to nyc freeassange.org
and uh and donate us a directly goes to what
stella had just uh informed us on and or you
can go to stella morris with one r uh at one at
twitter and uh and please folks uh around the
world uh let's do it tell everybody and let's
this is a we're in we're in the in the barricades
right now and we got to keep fighting i want to
thank you stella we're going to let you go
uh here at this point we're gonna come back
uh with one and dan you stay there you're a
good co-host uh so i'm gonna keep you there
stella uh we'll be in touch uh thank you once
again uh stella morris uh human rights attorney
and the partner of julian assange give chilling
in my love will you fella thanks i will thank
you thank you everyone all right i think we'll be
right back this is a little piece by um by niels
melzer and we'll be right back with robert boyle
one of the uh who provided testimony last week
we'll be right back this is nils melzer playing
moonlight sonata don't go anywhere anybody
do
okay that was moonlight sonata who knew that uh
niels melzer who gave me that piece of music uh
played classic piano uh i'm random critical random
critical live on fly here with a special edition
of live on the flyers on to countdown
the freedom here in new york city wbai
um and we're covering the assange uh hearing last
week and one of those and we got daniel ellsberg
in the my co-pilot today one an honor that is
we have robert boyle who provided testimony
for during the hearing last year and uh last week
during the appeal robert boyle is a great attorney
an old friend of mine and a student of william
kunsler uh welcome back to the show robert
thank you for having me randy and hello to
uh someone i really look up to mr ellsberg
honor to be with you thank you all right so
uh go ahead uh bob last week uh the u.s uh
u.s government uh they said that julian's okay the
conditions are great in this country he doesn't
face risk he doesn't face you know depression
and suicide what did you actually submit there
could you summarize that for us sure um in support
of its appeal the u.s government gave so-called
assurances to the uh presiding officials in the
uk uh you know as you know the uh extradition
request was turned down uh not on the merits but
on the fact that the english government could not
be assured that julian assange's
mental and emotional health would be
would be sustained should he be transferred to
a u.s prison and we know that he suffered you
know up until now um and so they they made certain
representations which um as a federal practitioner
here in the states i was asked to review them
and to to point out to the court you know the the
holes in them you know that that are the size of a
mack truck so basically they say well first of all
we're not going to put mr assange under what's
known as the sam special administrative measures
unless of course they say you know he does
something to justify imposition of the sams
well you know right there that leaves it totally
up to the u.s government as to whether anything
he does be it speak to the media be it
um you know writing articles can justify
being put under special administrative
measures and what what they are are a great um
prohibition on communication with
people in the outside world under
special administrative measures individuals
who are incarcerated and there are a lot in
this country under special administrative
measures can only speak to certain people
if any they're denied contact with
other inmates and for example i've had
clients under special administrative measures
and um you know i'm not allowed to um
under contempt of court i'm not allowed to say
anything about the substance of what they tell me
even if it's not i mean i don't do that anyway in
terms of attorney-client communications but even
confidential communications i can't discuss it
with anyone now the government says well we won't
put mr assange under a special administrative
measures well you know the sams are onerous but
being in a maximum security prison in this country
is onerous and denies much communication with the
outside world under general bop regulations
um you're only allowed to communicate with
immediate family your letters are censored
and letters coming in are censored um your uh
only allowed a certain minimum number of
visits and only then with immediate family
and in many of the maximum security prisons
in the federal system those visits are not
contact visits they're through plexiglas so these
are the you know even without the sands these are
the conditions that julian assange will be under
should he be extradited to this country now also
the u.s government makes the representation that
since the united states and australia are part
of a treaty and not an extradition
treaty but a repatriation treaty
julian assange the u.s would not oppose the
transfer of julian assange to a prison in
australia should he be convicted in this country
well you know that's another you know very
vague so-called promise first of all the u the
australian government has not consented to that
so that would um obviously be necessary
secondly we're talking something that's
years down the road at that point and this
gets to another i think important point that um
should mr assange be extradited to this country
his criminal defense and the preparation for
trial will only really begin at that point it
could be a year or more after he's extradited that
trial would even commence wow um the trial itself
could take months because it's a complicated
case involving you know tens of thousands of
documents um if he is convicted it's
not unusual in the federal system for
the sentencing proceeding to take place four to
five months after the jury's verdict wow then you
um once he's sentenced of course he has the
right to appeal to the federal court of appeals
in my experience in complex cases it takes two
to three years for those appeals to be resolved
because the the record is enormous you have
to write a brief the government has to write
a brief you get to reply then it's put on the
court's calendar then it's set for oral argument
and then the court issues a decision but the court
can take however long it wants to issue a decision
wow and it's in in a in that situation so um the
government is making the us government is making
the argument to the uk government well you know
he's uh you know not gonna be in um uh you know
max conditions for very long but the um uh the
situation is he'll be under under in intensely um
egregiously conditions you know on you know while
he is uh awaiting trial and even after trial
even if australia would would consent to uh to
take him which is something you know obviously
we want to win at trial but um it's going to be
here all right we have been talking we only have
a minute left i mean really a minute daniel if you
have uh very very um cogent points you made there
uh bob uh mr ellsberg if you have we have one
minute anything you want to add to that they're
not gonna have to say oh i've i've been listening
and learned a lot not all good news from ben
weisner but i i loved hearing from stella morris
i'm so uh it i i believe the us government wants
julian assange to die in prison and if that's
uh i don't think they want a trial here they
don't want these issues debated or
the immediate to take more concern
than they do when he's rotting in a british jail
so i don't think they want him over here they
want him endlessly in that belmarsh prison
and uh to die there and it's i think it's
the knowledge of our support and the programs like
this in all around the world and above all as i
said earlier that he has stella morris and two
children waiting for him and supporting him now
that we'll keep him alive and i don't want to
see him die in that person i want to see him out
right and that can only be done really by the u.s
dropping these charges and that's what president
biden should do absolutely all right uh bob
30 seconds any conclusion in 30 seconds here
well there's not much more that i did than what mr
ellsberg said but you know the conditions in u.s
prisons are horrendous right horrendous it's
uh it's a death sentence to be sentenced you
know into one of these places and we must
fight to prevent julian assange from ever
coming back here okay uh that's the last word
i want to thank uh bob robert boyle attorney
robert boyle the great whistleblower legendary
whistleblower a real hero of mine and everybody
else and that is um mr daniel ellsberg i want to
thank stella morris and uh ben weisner and john
kiriakou we're going to go out this is a little
bit of my forgotten man this is from gold diggers
of 33. this is uh joan blondell it's an anti-war
song from world war one put a rifle in his hand
you sent him far away you shouted
hip hooray but look at him today
remember my forgotten man
you had him cultivate the land
he walked behind a plow the sweat fell
from his brow but look at him right now
and once he used to love me
i was happy then
he used to take care of this is
julian assange you're listening to
wbai new york stay strong and keep listening